<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://vault.tei-c.org/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://vault.tei-c.org/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_all.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
 <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Monſieur Acarete du Biscay's Journey from Buenos Ayres to Peru</title>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
           <p/>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
           <p/>
        </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
   <body>
   <pb n="24"/>
   <head>Monſieur Acarete du Biscay's Journey from Buenos Ayres to Peru</head>
     <div>
    <p>
 <lb/> I Left <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>, and took the Road I  <lb/> to <placeName>Cordoua</placeName>, leaving <placeName>Santa Fe</placeName> on my <lb/> right hand, of which place take this ac- <lb/>count, 'tis a Spaniſh Settlement dependant <lb/>upon <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>, the Commander is  <lb/>no more than a Lieutenant, and does no- <lb/>thing but by order from the Governor  <lb/>of <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>. 'Tis a little place con- <lb/>taining 25 <choice> <orig>Houfes,</orig> <reg>Houses</reg> </choice> without any Walls,  <lb/>Fortifications, or Garriſon, diſtant 80 <lb/>Leagues from <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName> Northward, <lb/>Situate upon the <geogName>River de la Plata</geogName>, large <lb/>Veſſels might come up to it, were it not <lb/>for a great bank that obstructs the pas- <lb/>sage a little above <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>. Ne- <lb/>vertheleſs 'tis a very advantageous Poſt, <lb/>because 'tis the only passage from <placeName>Peru</placeName>, <lb/><placeName>Chili</placeName> and <placeName>Tucuman</placeName> to <placeName>Paraguay</placeName>, and in a <lb/>manner the Magazine of the Commodi-
 </p>

<pb n="25"/>
     <div>
      <p>
 <lb/>ties drawn from thence, particularly that <lb/>Herb already <choice> <orig>ſpoken</orig> <reg>spoken</reg> </choice> of, which they <lb/>cannot be without in thoſe Provinces. <lb/>The Soil is as good and Fertile here as <lb/>at <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName> ; and the Town having <lb/>nothing remarkably different from what <lb/>has been <choice> <orig>observ'd</orig> <reg>observed</reg> </choice> of <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>, I <lb/>leave it, and proceed upon my Jour- <lb/>ney. 'Tis counted 140 Leagues from <lb/><placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName> to <placeName>Cordoua</placeName>, and <choice> <orig>becauſe</orig> <reg>because</reg> </choice> <lb/>ſome parts of the Road are uninhabited  <lb/>for a long way together; I ſurnished my <choice> <orig>felf</orig> <reg>self</reg> </choice> at <lb/>my departure with what I <lb/>was inform'd I <choice> <orig>fhould</orig> <reg>should</reg> </choice> <choice> <orig>ftand</orig> <reg>stand</reg> </choice> in need <lb/>of; ſo I ſet out having a Savage for my <lb/>Guide, with Three <choice> <orig>Hofes</orig> <reg>Horses</reg> </choice> and Three <lb/>Mules, ſome to carry my Baggage, and <lb/>the <choice> <orig>reft</orig> <reg>rest</reg> </choice> to change upon the way when <lb/>that I rid upon was tired. <lb/>From <placeName>Buenos Ayres</placeName>, to the <geogName>River Lu <lb/>can</geogName>, and even as far as the <geogName>River Recife</geogName>, <lb/>30 Leagues, I pass’d by several Habita <lb/>tions and Farms cultivated by the Spani- <lb/>ards, but beyond Recife to the <geogName>River <lb/>Salladillo</geogName>, I <choice> <orig>faw</orig> <reg>saw</reg> </choice> none. Let it be obſer- <lb/>ved by the way, that theſe Rivers as well <lb/>as all the reſt in the Provinces of <placeName>Buenos <lb/>Ayres</placeName>, <placeName>Paraguay</placeName> and <placeName>Tucuman</placeName>, that fall <lb/>into the <geogName>River de la Plata</geogName> are fordable <lb/>on <choice> <orig>horfe</orig> <reg>horse
</reg> </choice> -back; but when the Rains or <lb/> <fw type="catch">any</fw>
   </p>
   </div>

    </body>

 </text>
</TEI>