<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="https://vault.tei-c.org/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="https://vault.tei-c.org/P5/current/xml/tei/custom/schema/relaxng/tei_simplePrint.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
 <teiHeader>
     <fileDesc>
        <titleStmt>
           <title>Digital edition of <choice><orig>Monſieur</orig><reg>Monsieur</reg></choice> Acarete du Biscay's Journey from Buenos Ayres to Peru</title>
           <author>Alice Bi, Julieta Goldsmidt,  Nery González, Carlos Nusch </author>
        </titleStmt>
        <publicationStmt>
           <publisher>Copycats University Press</publisher>
           <date>2022</date>
        </publicationStmt>
        <sourceDesc>
           <bibl>
           <author>Acarete Du Biscay</author>
           <title>Monſieur Acarete du Biscay's Journey from Buenos Ayres to Peru</title>
           <pubPlace>Buenos Aires </pubPlace>
           <date>1867</date>
           <biblScope unit="page">pp.24-25</biblScope>
           </bibl>
        </sourceDesc>
     </fileDesc>
 </teiHeader>
 <text>
<body>
   <pb n="24"/>
   <head><choice><orig>Monſieur</orig><reg>Monsieur</reg></choice> Acarete du Biscay's Journey from Buenos Ayres to Peru</head>
    <p>
<lb/>I Left <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, and took the Road I  <lb/> to <name type="place">Cordoua</name>, leaving <name type="place">Santa Fe</name> on my <lb/> right hand, of which place take this ac <lb/>count, 'tis a Spaniſh Settlement dependant <lb/>upon <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, the Commander is  <lb/>no more than a Lieutenant, and does no <lb/>thing but by order from the Governor  <lb/>of <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>. 'Tis a little place con <lb/>taining <measure type= "cardinal"> <num> 25 </num> <choice> <orig>Houfes</orig> <reg>Houses</reg> </choice> </measure>, without any Walls,  <lb/>Fortifications, or Garriſon, diſtant <measure type= "distance"> <num> 80 Leagues </num> </measure> <lb/> from <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name> Northward, <lb/>Situate upon the <name type="placeGeog">River de la Plata</name>, large <lb/>Veſſels might come up to it, were it not <lb/>for a great bank that obstructs the pas <lb/>sage a little above <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>. Ne <lb/>vertheleſs 'tis a very advantageous Poſt, <lb/>because 'tis the only passage from <name type="place">Peru</name>, <lb/><name type="place">Chili</name> and <name type="place">Tucuman</name> to <name type="place">Paraguay</name>, and in a <lb/>manner the Magazine of the Commodi
 </p>

<pb n="25"/>
      <p>
 <lb/>ties drawn from thence, particularly that <lb/>Herb already <choice> <orig>ſpoken</orig> <reg>spoken</reg> </choice> of, which they <lb/>cannot be without in thoſe Provinces. <lb/>The Soil is as good and Fertile here as <lb/>at <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name> ; and the Town having <lb/>nothing remarkably different from what <lb/>has been <choice> <orig>observ'd</orig> <reg>observed</reg> </choice> of <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, I <lb/>leave it, and proceed upon my Jour <lb/>ney. 'Tis counted <measure type= "distance"> <num> 140 Leagues </num> </measure> from <lb/><name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name> to <name type="place">Cordoua</name>, and <choice> <orig>becauſe</orig> <reg>because</reg> </choice> <lb/>ſome parts of the Road are uninhabited  <lb/>for a long way together; I ſurnished my <choice> <orig>felf</orig> <reg>self</reg> </choice> at <lb/>my departure with what I <lb/>was inform'd I <choice> <orig>fhould</orig> <reg>should</reg> </choice> <choice> <orig>ftand</orig> <reg>stand</reg> </choice> in need <lb/>of; ſo I ſet out having a Savage for my <lb/>Guide, with <measure type= "ordinal"> <num> Three </num>  <choice> <orig>Hofes</orig> <reg>Horses</reg> </choice></measure> and <measure type= "ordinal"> <num> Three Mules </num> </measure> <lb/>, ſome to carry my Baggage, and <lb/>the <choice> <orig>reft</orig> <reg>rest</reg> </choice> to change upon the way when <lb/>that I rid upon was tired. <lb/>From <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, to the <name type="placeGeog">River Lu<lb/>can</name>, and even as far as the <name type="placeGeog">River Recife</name>, <lb/>30 Leagues, I pass’d by several Habita<lb/>tions and Farms cultivated by the Spani<lb/>ards, but beyond Recife to the <name type="placeGeog">River <lb/>Salladillo</name>, I <choice> <orig>faw</orig> <reg>saw</reg> </choice> none. Let it be <choice><orig>obſer<lb/>ved</orig><reg>observed</reg></choice> by the way, that <choice><orig>theſe</orig><reg>these</reg></choice> Rivers as well <lb/>as all the <choice><orig>reſt</orig><reg>choice</reg></choice> in the Provinces of <name type="place">Buenos <lb/>Ayres</name>, <name type="place">Paraguay</name> and <name type="place">Tucuman</name>, that fall <lb/>into the <name type="placeGeog">River de la Plata</name> are fordable <lb/>on <choice> <orig>horfe</orig> <reg>horse
</reg> </choice>-back; but when the Rains or <lb/> <fw type="catch">any</fw>
   </p>

<pb n="26"/>
   <p>
<lb/>other accident <choice> <orig>ſwells</orig><reg>swells</reg> </choice> them, a <lb/>Traveller <choice> <orig>muſt</orig> <reg>must</reg></choice> either <choice><orig>ſwim</orig> <reg>swim</reg></choice> over, or <choice><orig>elſe</orig> <reg>else</reg></choice> get <lb/>upon a bundle in the nature of a raft, <lb/>which a Savage hawls over to the other <lb/><choice><orig>ſide</orig> <reg>side</reg></choice>. I could not Swim, and <choice><orig>ſo</orig> <reg>so</reg></choice> was <lb/>forc'd to make <choice><orig>uſe</orig> <reg>use</reg></choice> of this expedient <lb/> <measure type="ordinal"> <num> twice or thrice  </num> </measure> when I could not find a <lb/>Ford. The way was this, my <!--<emph style="font-style: italic">Indian</emph>--> <lb/>kill'd a Wild Bull, flead the Hide off, <lb/>
<choice><orig>ſtuffed</orig> <reg>stuffed</reg></choice> it with <choice><orig>ſtraw</orig> <reg>straw</reg></choice>, and ty'd it up in <lb/>a great bundle with thongs of the <choice><orig>ſame</orig> <reg>same</reg></choice> <lb/>Hide, upon which I plac'd my <choice><orig>ſelf</orig> <reg>self</reg></choice> with <lb/> my Baggage ; he <choice><orig>ſwam</orig><reg>swam</reg></choice> over hawling me <lb/>after him by a Cord ty'd to the bundle, <lb/>and then he repaſs'd and <choice><orig>ſwam</orig> <reg>swam</reg></choice> my <choice><orig>Horſes</orig> <reg>Horses</reg></choice> <lb/>and Mules over to me.</p>
   
   <p>
<lb/>All the Country between the <name type="placeGeog">River <lb/>Recife</name> and <name type="place">Salladillo</name>, tho' uninhabited, <lb/>abounds in Cattle and all ſorts of Fruit <lb/>trees, except Walnut and Chesnut-trees; <lb/>there are whole Woods of Nectarine-<lb/>Trees, Three or Four Leagues in <choice><orig>compaſs</orig><reg>compass</reg></choice>, <lb/>that bear excellent Fruit, which they <lb/>not only eat raw, but bake them, or dry <lb/>them in the Sun, to keep, as we in <name type="place">France</name> <lb/> do Prunes: They <choice><orig>ſeldom uſe</orig><reg>seldom use</reg></choice> any other <lb/>than the Wood of this Tree for common <lb/>firing at <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, and thereabouts. <lb/>The Savages that dwell in <choice><orig>theſe</orig><reg>these</reg></choice> Parts are <lb/><choice><orig>diſtinguiſh'd</orig> <reg>distinguished</reg></choice> into two sorts, those that <fw type="catch">voluntarily</fw></p>

<p>
<choice><orig>ſubmit</orig><reg>Submit</reg></choice> to the Spaniards are call’d <choice><orig>Panpiſtas</orig><reg>Panpistas</reg></choice>, the <choice><orig>reſt</orig><reg>rest</reg></choice> Serranos, both cloathed with Skins, but the <choice><orig>laſt ſet</orig><reg>last set</reg></choice> up on the <choice><orig>Panpiſtas</orig><reg>Panpistas</reg></choice> as their mortal Enemies wherever they meet with them. All Fight on Horſe-back, either with Lances pointed with Iron or Bones ſharpen'd, or else with Bows and Arrows, they wear Bulls-hides faſhion'd like a Doublet without ſleeves, to defend their Bodies. Their Chiefs that command over them in War and Peace, are call’d Couracas. When they take any one of their Enemies, alive or dead, they meet all together, and after they have reproach'd him, that either he or his Relations were the death of their Kindred or Friends, they cut and tear him into pieces, which they roaſt a little and eat, making a drinking Bowl of his Scull. They feed moſtly upon flesh either raw or dreſs'd, and particularly Colts fleſh, which they like! better than Veal. They catch abundance of Fiſh likewiſe in their Rivers, They have no ſettled places of aboad, but ramble up and down, ſeveral Families together, and live in Tents. </p>
<p>
I could not inform my ſelf exactly what Religion they were of, but I was told that they look'd upon the Sun and Moon as Deities and as I travell'd along, I ſaw a Savage upon his knees with his Face to the Sun, who cry'd out and made ſtrange geſtures with his Hands and Arms. I learn'd from the Savage that accompany'd me, that he was one of thoſe they call'd Papas, who in the Morning kneel towards the Sun, and at Night towards the Moon, to ſupplicate those fancy'd Divinities to be propitious to them, to give them fair Weather, and Victory over their Foes. 
</p>
<p>
They make no great Ceremony in their Marriages ; but when a Relation dies, after they have rubb’d his body with a certain Earth that conſumes all but the Bones, they preserve them, and carry as many of them as they can conveniently about with them in a ſort of Cheſts, and this they do in token of their affection to their Kindred ; indeed they are not wanting in good Offices to them during their Lives, nor in their Sickneſs and Death. 
</p>
<p>
Along the <name type="placeGeog"> River Salladillo </name>, I took notice of a great many Parrats, or Papagays, as the Spaniards call them, and certain Birds, call’d Guacamayos, which are of divers Colours, and twice or thrice as big as a Parrat. The River it ſelf is full of the Fiſh, call'd Dorado, which is very good to eat. There is alſo a Creature in it, whether 'tis Meat or Poyſon no body knows, it has Four Feet and a long Tail like a Lizard. 
</p>
<p>From <name type="place"> Salladillo </name> quite to <name type="place"> Cordoua </name>, you go along a very fine River, that abounds with Fiſh, which is neither wide nor deep, for it may be forded over. On the Bank of it you meet with little Plan tations every Three or Four Leagues ; which are like Country Houſes inhabited by Spaniards, Portuguese, and the Natives, who have all the neceſſary accomodations of Life they can wiſh, and are very Civil and Charitable to Strangers; their principal Wealth is in Horſes and Mules, in which they Trade with the Inhabitants of Peru. </p>
<p>
<name type="place">Cordoua </name> is a Town Situate in a pleaſant and fruitful Plain upon the ſide of a River, bigger and broader than that I have juſt ſpoken of : 'Tis compos’d of about <measure type="cardinal"> <num>400 Houses </num> </measure>, Built like thoſe of <name type="place"> Buenos Ayres </name> . It has neither Ditches, nor Walls, nor Fort for its defence; He that Commands it is Governor of all the Provinces of <name type="place">Tucuman </name>, and tho’ it be the place of his ordinary Residence, yet he is wont now and then, as he ſees occaſion, to go and paſs ſome time at <name type="place">St. Jago de l’Eſtro </name> , at <name type="place">St. Miguel de Tucuman </name> , (which is the Capital City of the Province) at <name type="place">Salta </name> and at <name type="place">Xuxui </name>. In each of theſe Villages there is a Lieutenant, who has under him an Alcalde and ſome Officers for the Adminiſtration of Juſtice. The Biſhop of <name type="place">Tucuman</name> likewiſe uſually reſides at <name type="place">Cordoua </name>, where the Cathedral is the only Pariſh Church of the whole Town, but there are divers Convents of Monks, namely of Dominicans, Recollects, and those of the Order de la Mercy: and one of Nunns. The Jesuits have a College there, and their Chappel is the fineſt and richeſt of all. 
</p>
<p>
The Inhabitants are Rich in Gold and Silver, which they get by the Trade they have for Mules, with which they furniſh <name type="place"> Peru </name> and other Parts; which is ſo conſiderable, that they ſell about <measure type="cardinal"> <num> 28 or 30000  </num> </measure> of 'em every Year, which they breed up in their Farms. They usually keep 'em till they are about <measure type="cardinal"> <num>  Two Years old </num> </measure> , then expose 'em to Sale, and have about <measure type="currency"> <num> Six Patagons </num> </measure>  a piece for 'em. The Merchants that come to buy 'em, carry 'em to <name type="place">  St. Jago</name>, to <name type="place"> Salta </name> and <name type="place"> Xuxui</name>  , where they leave 'em for Three Years, till they are well grown and become ſtrong, and afterwards bring 'em to <name type="place">Peru </name>, where they preſently have Vent for 'em, becauſe there as well as in the reſt of the Western part of America, the greateſt part of their Carriage is upon Mules. The People of <name type="place">Cordoua</name> alſo drive a Trade in Cows, which they have from the Countrey of <name type="place">Buenos Ayres</name>, and carry to <name type="place"> Peru </name>, where without this way of Subſiſtance 'tis certain they would have much ado to live. This kind of Traffick makes this Town the moſt conſiderable in the Province of <name type="place">Tucuman </name>, as well for its Riches and Commodities, as for the Number of its Inhabitants, which are counted to be at leaſt <measure type="cardinal"> <num> 5 or 600 Families </num> </measure>, beſides Slaves who are <measure type="ordinal"> <num> three times  </num> </measure> the number. But the gene rality of 'em of all degrees have no other Arms but a Sword and Poignard, and are very indifferent Souldiers, the Air of the Country, and the Plenty they enjoy, rendring them Lazy and Cowardly. 
</p>
</body>
</text>


</TEI>